Guide to the Nicole Baran Papers SC1269
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Nicole Baran papers
1994-2015
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Baran, Nicole
SC1269
40 Linear Feet (31 boxes)
21 megabyte(s) (5 .pdf files)
Biographical / Historical
Nicole Baran is from San Francisco and received her BA and MA in English from Stanford University (2000 and 2001) and Masters in Social Work (MSW) from Washington University in St. Louis (2003), with a specialization in management and a focus on domestic violence research. Nicole founded the Center for Relationship Abuse Awareness (the Center) in 2005, a nonprofit that educates and trains communities, institutions and young leaders to take action to end violence against women. As of 2015, the Center’s website, www.stoprelationshipabuse.org, provides professional resources to an average of 40,000 unique visitors per month from 196 countries. Nicole taught in the Feminist Studies Program at Stanford University from 2006-2007 to 2013-2014 after developing the course FEMST 138/238 (FEMGEN 138/238) Violence Against Women: Theories, Issues, and Prevention. She changed the course in 2016-2017 to Men’s Violence Against Women: A Social & Critical Analysis.
The motivation to start the Center and include a Stanford student leadership program was inspired by the concept that Stanford is a leader in research and innovation-- why can’t it be a leader in ending violence against women? In 2006, Nicole successfully partnered with Stanford University to institutionalize a comprehensive response to gender-based violence on campus. Stanford hired the Center to manage a five-year grant from the USJDOJ Office on Violence Against Women; Nicole also wrote the proposal to the provost in 2010 to establish Stanford’s first Office on Sexual Assault and Relationship Abuse (SARA). In her 2014 op-ed in the Stanford Daily, “Stanford Drops the Ball on Sexual Assault Cases,” Nicole writes “The Center wrote the proposal to establish the Office of Sexual Assault and Relationship Abuse in hopes that an official office would lead to greater change, but until the SARA office reports directly to the Provost or President of the University, we will continue to see ineffective and inadequate responses to these issues.” She writes, “The Center decided to stop working with Stanford in 2011 largely due to the fact that the people in power at Stanford continued to prioritize liability over student safety.”
Prior to the Center for Relationship Abuse Awareness, she was the Grant and Contract Manager at the Support Network for Battered Women in Mountain View. Previously, she worked for the Greenbook Initiative (a national collaboration) in St. Louis and produced state guidelines regarding the response of domestic violence service providers to the co-occurrence of child maltreatment and domestic violence. She conducted national trainings and contributed to publications to improve the institutional response to gender-based violence from 2001-2015. She delivered over 350 customized workshops to organizations such as Kaiser Permanente, the San Francisco Bar Association, the Family Violence Prevention Fund (Futures Without Violence), and CPEDV, California’s State Domestic Violence Coalition. One of her specific research areas was analyzing the impact of the anti-feminist backlash on research and practices in the movement to end gender-based violence.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Nicole Baran, 2015.
Scope and Contents
Materials related to the course developed by Nicole Baran, FEMST 138/238 (FEMGEN 138/238): Violence Against Women: Theories, Issues and Prevention, and materials related to the nonprofit created by Nicole Baran, the Center for Relationship Abuse Awareness (founded 2005). Includes outside training manuals and research articles used to inform the work; training materials and handouts, organization and program documents, correspondence, intern projects and materials; 2010 proposal to establish the first Office of Sexual Assault and Relationship Abuse at Stanford; publication for the Greenbook Initiative; MSW papers; research articles and presentations about the backlash against the movement to end gender-based violence; Stanford Daily Op-Ed critiquing Stanford’s response to sexual violence in 2014; and website of the Center for Relationship Abuse Awareness, www.stoprelationshipabuse.org
Conditions Governing Access
Series 1-2, 4-9, 19-29, and 32-38 are restricted until 2026; Series 31 is restricted until 2066.
Series 3, 10-18, 30, and 39 are open for research use; materials must be requested at least 48 hours in advance of intended use. Audio-visual materials are not available in original format, and must be reformatted to a digital use copy.
Family violence.; Women -- Crimes against.; Women -- Violence against.; Relationship abuse.; Sexual assault.; Sexual violence.; Domestic violence.; FEMST 138; Violence against women -- Theories and prevention.; Baran, Nicole; Baran, Nicole; Center For Relationship Abuse Awareness.; Stanford University. Office of Sexual Assault & Relationship Abuse Education & Response (SARA).
- Papers, Accession ARCH-2015-156
  - Memorabilia, Series 1
    Conditions Governing Access
    Materials in this series are restricted until 2026.
    - Memorabilia Binder
      - Table of Contents (Box 16)
        Related Materials
        See electronic records series for inventory.
      - Speaking Truth Moving Sand: Why It Matters, 2014 (Box 16)
        Scope and Contents
        Stanford Women's Leadership Conference. Baran was asked to speak about how she got to where she is professionally. Baran spoke about Stanford controversies and burn-out.
        Includes full PowerPoint.
        See electronic records series for details.
      - History of Beliefs (Box 16)
      - Letter from Founder (Box 16)
      - High School Op-Ed, 1996 (Box 16)
      - Interview with Nicole Baran Seneca International, 2013 (Box 16)
      - “Maestro Market Interview”, 2012 (Box 16)
      - Speeches (Box 16)
      - Victim Blaming speech, 2007 (Box 16)
      - Take Back the Night Speeches, 2007-2011 (Box 16)
      - Progress Reports Fundraising Letters, 2006-2011 (Box 16)
      - Testimonials (Box 16)
      - Center Programming Testimonials (Box 16)
      - FEMST 138/238 Testimonials, 2012 (Box 16)
      - Accomplishments (Box 16)
      - Nicole Baran Resume, 2014 (Box 16)
      - Nicole Op-Ed: Stanford Drops the Ball on Sexual Assault Case, 2014 (Box 16)
        Baran's 2014 Stanford Daily critique of how Stanford responds to sexual violence. Includes twitter screen shot.
      - League of Women Voters, 2011 (Box 16)
        Baran was honored as a Rising Star by the SF League of Women Voters, along with Jennifer Siebel Newsom.
      - SF Examiner, “Celebrating 100 Years of Suffrage”, 2011 Feb 15 (Box 16)
      - Some Emails, 2006-2008 (Box 16)
      - to anne firth murray email. you are inspiring and I am tired, 2014 (Box 16)
      - Center Brochures (Box 16)
      - Newspaper Articles about Center, 2007, 2010 (Box 16)
      - Promotional Materials (Box 16)
      - Volunteer Intern Thank Yous (Box 16)
      - Client Thank Yous (Box 16)
      - Org Participant Numbers: All, 2006-2014 (Box 16)
      - Participant Numbers: Stanford University, 2006-2010 (Box 16)
    - How to Develop an Intern Program
      - How to Develop an Manual Created by Center: How to Develop an Intern Program to End VAW, 2012 (Box 16)
        This manual can be found at www.stoprelationshipabuse.org and can be used by any organization or intern wishing to start an intern program.
    - Miscellaneous Memorabilia
      - Office Library Bibliography - Books and Media, 2015 (Box 16)
        - Office Library - Books (Box 16)
        - Office Library - Media (Box 16)
      - Feminist Studies Posters (Box 16)
      - Nicole on KQED - Forum (Box 16)
      - Mirkarimi, 2013 (Box 16)
        Includes the notes and speech for Baran's city hall statement calling on city council to remove SF Sheriff Mirkarimi from office after he was charged with domestic violence. Mirkarimi was not removed and attended a batterer's intervention program, which is what the sheriff is responsible for overseeing.
    - Board Orientation Manual
      - Organization Information (Box 16)
      - Community/Public Relations (Box 16)
      - Finances (Box 16)
      - Board Operations (Box 16)
      - Fundraising (Box 16)
      - Corporate Documents (Box 16)
      - Domestic Violence Information (Box 16)
      - Agendas/Minutes (Box 16)
  - Provost Proposal, Series 2
    In 2010, Baran was asked by the Provost, John Etchemendy, to write a proposal to establish the first office of sexual assault and relationship abuse at Stanford.
    - Stanford Pay Structure, 2010 (Box 16)
    - Provost Proposal Prep, 2010 (Box 16)
      After asking for input and feedback from relevant department heads, a delay of 5 weeks from Baran's initial proposal draft occurred due to one department head’s refusal to budge on changing the percentage of time allocated to direct service (advocacy) by the director; he wanted it to be 25% without relevant rationale. Baran had made it 5% while allocating a full time position to direct service in order to ensure the director, with limited resources and staff, would have time to properly train all other first responders and make important policy changes without being pulled away for advocacy services that could be conducted by the full time advocacy position written into the proposal. This is consistent with best practices. The justification for this allocation by Baran is included in this folder. See Memorabilia Binder for unsent letter by Baran about this incident; it is in Speaking Truth and Moving Sand.
    - Original Job Description (with 5%) - Proposal, 2010 (Box 16)
      Ultimately, Nicole was forced to change it to 20% from 5%.
    - Final Proposal, 2010 (Box 16)
    - Job Descriptions, 2010 (Box 16)
    - Office Flowchart, 2010 (Box 16)
    - Angela Exson, 2010 (Box 16)
  - FEMST 138: Violence Against Women: Theory, Issues and Prevention Course Readers, Series 3
    The course reader for 2013 was online instead; there were changes from 2012.
    - Entire Course Reader originals (Box 7)
    - Problematic Quotes, 2013 (Box 7)
    - VAW Articles and Literature (Box 7)
    - Additions, 2008 (Box 7)
    - Old Course Readings, 2007 Winter (Box 7)
    - Articles removed from syllabus (Box 7)
    - Optional Readings (Box 7)
    - Course Reader, 2007 (Box 7)
    - Course Reader, 2008 (Box 7)
    - Course Reader, 2009 (Box 7)
    - Course Reader, 2010 (Box 7)
    - Course Reader, 2011 (Box 7)
    - Course Reader, 2012 (Box 7)
  - FEMST 138: Violence Against Women: Theories, Issues, and Prevention Course Materials, Series 4
    As with all of the training materials, the handouts and PowerPoints are incomplete without the verbal presentation associated with them.
    - Course Development
      - Initial Feminist Studies Correspondence (Box 31)
        This was the initial correspondence by Baran to house the formerly PEDS 215 course as a Feminist Studies course.
      - Gender GER Rationale/WAYS (Box 31)
      - Directed Reading Proposal (Box 31)
      - Course Justification, 2011 (Box 31)
      - Humbio Proposal, 2012 (Box 31)
      - FEMST 100 Proposal, 2013 Jan 24 (Box 31)
      - Course Development (not complete) (Box 31)
      - Syllabi to Review (not complete) (Box 31)
      - Curriculum Ideas (not complete) (Box 31)
      - What Love Means (Box 31)
    - Folder Organization for Course, 2013
      These files were used to organize the course each year, often by an intern.
      - For Instructor Tuesday (Box 31)
      - For Instructor Thursday, 2013 (Box 31)
      - Sign-In Sheets, 2013 (Box 31)
      - Handouts for Students, 2013 (Box 31)
      - Course Assignments, 2013 (Box 31)
      - Syllabus, 2013 (Box 31)
      - Service Learning, 2013 (Box 31)
      - Extra Handouts, 2013 (Box 31)
      - Pre-Tests (Blank), 2013 (Box 31)
      - Make-Up Work, 2013 (Box 31)
      - Research Proposals, 2013 (Box 31)
      - Reading Journals, 2013 (Box 31)
      - Graded Reading Journal, 2013 (Box 31)
      - Safety Plans, 2013 (Box 31)
      - Graded Safety Plan, 2013 (Box 31)
      - Lit. Review, 2013 (Box 31)
      - Post/Pre Tests (Completed), 2013 (Box 31)
    - Course Information, 2012 Fall
      - Course Information, 2012 Fall (Box 31)
    - Course Handouts by Class, 2011
      - Course Reader Table of Contents/Syllabus, 2013 (Box 31)
      - Week 1A - Introduction Readings, 2011 Fall (Box 31)
      - Week 1B - Interpersonal Institutional Tactics, 2011 Fall (Box 31)
      - Week 2A - Masculinity Violence, 2011 Fall (Box 31)
      - Week 2B - Femst Theories of Relationship Abuse, 2011 Fall (Box 31)
      - Week 3A - Heterosexism Same-Sex, 2011 Fall (Box 31)
      - Week 3B - Feminist Theories Sexual Violence, 2011 Fall (Box 31)
      - Week 4A - Integrating Theory into Practice, 2011 Fall (Box 31)
      - Week 4B - Defending Their Lives, 2011 Fall (Box 31)
      - Week 5A - Anti-Feminist Backlash, 2011 Fall (Box 31)
      - Week 5B - Feminist Theories Perspectives on Gender Violence, 2011 Fall (Box 31)
      - Week 6A - Tensions with Criminal Justice, 2011 Fall (Box 31)
      - Week 6B - Children/Teens College, 2011 Fall (Box 31)
      - Week 7A - Community Organizing, Helping Friends, 2011 Fall (Box 31)
      - Week 7B - Community Accountability, 2011 Fall (Box 31)
      - Week 8B - Anti-Violence Movement Building, 2011 Fall (Box 31)
      - Week 9A - Challenging Victim Blaming, 2011 Fall (Box 31)
      - Week 9B - Language Violence, Media Literacy, 2011 Fall (Box 31)
      - Week 10A - Presentations, 2011 Fall (Box 31)
      - Week 10B - Movement in Practice, 2011 Fall (Box 31)
      - Section Handouts (extra), 2011 Fall (Box 31)
    - Course Handouts, 2010
      - Day 1 Extra Handouts, 2010 (Box 31)
      - Day 3 Extra Handouts (LGBT), 2010 (Box 31)
      - Day 8 Backlash Handouts, 2010 (Box 31)
      - Day 9 Feminist Theories of Gender Violence, 2010 (Box 31)
      - Day 10 Children/Teens College, 2010 (Box 31)
      - Day 12 Extra Handouts (Transnational), 2010 (Box 31)
      - Day 14 Extra Handouts (Community Accountability), 2010 (Box 31)
      - Day 15 Extra Handouts, 2010 (Box 31)
      - Day 16 Media Handouts, 2010 (Box 31)
      - Day 17 Extra Handouts, 2010 (Box 31)
      - Day 18 FAQs, 2010 (Box 31)
      - Day 19 Course Evals, 2010 (Box 31)
      - Section F10, 2010 (Box 31)
      - Course Assignments, 2010 (Box 31)
      - For Section, Instructor Notes, 2010 (Box 31)
    - Syllabi
      - Syllabus, 2008 Fall (Box 31)
      - Syllabus, 2007 Spring (Box 31)
      - Syllabus, 2009 Fall (Box 31)
      - Syllabus, 2010 (Box 31)
    - Course Information, 2007 Winter
      - Course Information: Course Assignments, 2007 Winter (Box 31)
      - Course Information: Syllabus, 2007 Winter (Box 31)
    - Miscellaneous Handouts
      - In Class Handouts (Box 31)
      - Handouts Packet (Box 31)
      - Extra Copies - Readings/Articles (Box 31)
      - Handouts to be Distributed (Box 31)
      - Handout Originals (Box 31)
      - VAW Course Handouts (Box 31)
      - Legislative Successes (Box 31)
      - Poems (Box 31)
      - Electronic Handouts (Box 31)
  - FEMST 138: Violence Against Women: Theories, Issues, and Prevention Course Binders, Series 5
    Courses taught and developed by Nicole Baran: Violence Against Women: Theory, Issues and Prevention, Winter & Spring 2006/2007: PEDS 215. The course was first housed under Pediatrics until Fall 2007 when it became FEMST 138 Fall 2007: FEMST 138/238; Fall 2008: FEMST 138/238; Fall 2009: FEMST 138/238; Fall 2010: FEMST 138/238; Fall 2011: FEMST 138/238; Fall 2012: FEMST 138/238; Fall 2013: FEMGEN 138/238 (HUMBIO 178V).
    See Box 29 for FEMST 100.
    - Course Binders
      These were the course binders created by the Course Intern(s) and used by them to organize handouts, etc. Not all lesson plans are present (PowerPoints); not all handouts are present. These course binders do not reflect the course in its entirety.
      - Violence Against Women Course, 2007 Spring (Box 15)
      - Violence Against Women Course, 2008 Fall (Box 15)
      - Violence Against Women Course, 2009 Fall (Box 15)
      - Violence Against Women Course, 2010 Fall (Box 15)
      - Violence Against Women Course, 2011 Fall (Box 15)
      - Violence Against Women: Theory, Issues, and Prevention, Femstd. 138, 2012 Fall (Box 15)
      - "Violence Against Women: Theory, Issues, and Prevention" FEMGEN 138/238 (HUMBIO 178V), 2013 Fall (Box 15)
        - Course Documents (Box 15)
        - Evaluations and Pre/Post Tests (Box 15)
        - Student Submitted Quotes (Box 15)
        - 1A VAW as a Human Rights Issue: The Intersection of Oppression and Violence (Box 15)
        - 1B Understanding the Problem: Individual and Institutional Tactics of Power and Control (Box 15)
        - 2A Feminist Theories of Masculinity and Violence (Box 15)
        - 2B Feminist Theories of Relationship Abuse (Box 15)
        - 3A Heterosexism and Same-Gender Relationship Abuse (Box 15)
        - 3B Feminist Theories About Sexual Violence (Box 15)
        - 4A Feminist Perspectives on Gender Violence (Box 15)
        - 4B Integrating Theory and Practice: Research Methods (Box 15)
        - 5A Women's Voices: Defending Their Lives (Box 15)
        - 5B The Anti-Feminist Backlash: Gender Neutralization (Box 15)
        - 6A Tensions with the Criminal Justice System (Box 15)
        - 6B Systemic Re-Victimization of Children in the Context (Box 15)
        - 7A Community Organizing: Helping Friends Women- Defined Safety Planning (Box 15)
        - 7B Community Accountability (Box 15)
        - 8A Transnational Perspectives on Violence (Box 15)
        - 8B Anti-Feminist Movement Building (Box 15)
        - 9A Challenging Victim Blaming (Box 15)
        - 9B Media Violence Media Justice: A Critical Analysis (Box 15)
        - 10A Presentations: Frequently Asked Questions (Box 15)
        - 10B Movement in Practice: Challenges, Successes and Self-Care (Box 15)
  - Student Certification Training Seminar: FEMGEN 100, Series 6
    This was an 8-hour training that Baran delivered to interns and other student leaders. This box is incomplete as it does not have the trainings for 2012. through 2014. Baran ended up offering it as a course in 2013 called FEMGEN100: Awareness to Action Workshop: Ending Violence Against Women. This may be added later to the electronic records series. Coordinating this training was an intern project. Baran presented.
    - Awareness to Action, Participant Folder, 2013 May 18 (Box 29)
    - Certification, 2011 Apr 23 (Box 29)
    - Originals - Handouts to Copy (Box 29)
    - Freeze Scene - Actor Scripts (Box 29)
    - Presenter - Student Training Handouts (Box 29)
    - Yeardley Love Case (Box 29)
    - Student Cert - Extra Certificates (Box 29)
    - Student Certification, 2010 Jan 23 (Box 29)
    - Presenter Folder - Nicole (Box 29)
    - Actor Scripts, 2011 Apr 23 (Box 29)
    - Center Training Certificates (Box 29)
    - Relationship Abuse Training Seminar: Participant Folder Template, 2010 Spring (Box 29)
    - Presenter Folder Template, 2010 Spring (Box 29)
    - Student Training Seminar Handouts (Box 29)
    - FAQ from training for possible follow-up session, 2009 Jan 24 (Box 29)
    - Old Handouts (Box 29)
    - Student Training Seminar, 2009 Jan 24 (Box 29)
    - Presenter - Student Training (Box 29)
    - Presenter Folder Template, 2009 Spring (Box 29)
    - Relationship Abuse Training Seminar (Box 29)
    - Relationship Abuse Training Seminar: Sample Participant Folder, 2010 Jan 23 (Box 29)
    - Relationship Abuse Training Seminar: Participant Packet template (training), 2009 Apr 11 (Box 29)
  - Organization How-Tos, Series 7
    See Box 16 for the Center's manual on How to Start an Intern Program.
    - The Center How-To Binder
      This How-To Binder was created by interns over the years so that any task could be replicated by a new intern. This could be useful for people starting intern programs, but it is very specific to the Center.
      - AAA (Box 14)
      - Accounting (Box 14)
      - Administrative (Box 14)
      - Board of Directors (Box 14)
      - Direct Service (Box 14)
      - Dorm Outreach (Box 14)
      - Fundraising (Box 14)
      - Thank You's (Box 14)
      - Training (Box 14)
      - On Campus How to Run a Workshop (Box 14)
      - Volunteer Coordinator (Box 14)
      - Publicity (Box 14)
      - Grants (Box 14)
      - Facebook (Box 14)
      - Course (Box 14)
      - Tabling (Box 14)
      - Events (Box 14)
      - Positions (Box 14)
      - Website (Box 14)
      - Grant Deadlines (Box 14)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 14)
      - How to Create a Brochure (Box 14)
      - Old How-Tos (Box 14)
  - Intern/Next Generation Leadership Program, Series 8
    The Center managed between 5 to 20 interns at one time, including a summer internship program of 2-4 interns. It was started as a leadership program with the intent of creating opportunities for students to affect change in ending VAW in any discipline they chose. Once the Center started the OVW Grant at Stanford, the intern program became a project of the grant. When the Center left Stanford, the intern leadership program continued as the Next Generation Leadership Program.
    - Intern Program
      See Box 16 for the intern manual for more recent documents. The intern recruitment and application process was moved online to www.stoprelationshipabuse.org and has subsequently been removed. See electronic records series for details.
      - Intern Recruitment (Box 14)
      - Intern Interviews (Box 14)
      - Intern Onboarding (Box 14)
      - Intern Tasks Responsibilities (Box 14)
      - Sign Up Sheets (Box 14)
      - Recruitment (Box 14)
      - Summer Wrap Up Packets (Box 14)
      - Volunteer Orientation Manual (Box 14)
    - Young Women's Leadership Retreat
      This retreat was meant for interns or students from the region (including Santa Cruz and Berkeley) to take their activism to the next level.
      - Intern Program, Volunteer Orientation (Box 14)
      - YWLR Sample Participant Folder, 2012 May 19-20 (Box 14)
      - YWLR Sample Panelist Folder, 2012 May 19-20 (Box 14)
      - YWLR Sample Leader Folder, 2012 May 12-20 (Box 14)
      - Action Plans (Box 14)
    - Intern Projects
      These were sample projects that were part of the first-second group of student interns associated with the OVW Grant. Students were expected to choose a campus population for targeted educational activities.
      - Legislation (Box 14)
      - Student Committees (Box 14)
      - Intern Sustainability Packet: Is It Possible to Get Frat Guys to Care About Violence Against Women?, 2008 May 31 (Box 14)
      - Stanford Partnership to End Violence against Women: Intern Sustainability Plan June 12, 2008, 2008 Jun 12 (Box 14)
      - Final Sustainability Plan; Internship Winter 2007-Spring 2008, 2008 Jun 4 (Box 14)
      - Final Intern Plan: Latino Population (Box 14)
      - Final Report: Target Population - ISC Sororities, 2008 May 26 (Box 14)
      - Final Intern Sustainability Plan: Intern Coordinator, 2008 Jun (Box 14)
      - Intern Sustainability Plan: Men and Men Against Abuse Now (MAAN), 2008 May (Box 14)
  - Center Handouts, Series 9
    These handouts, including drafts, were used for Center trainings and workshops. Most of them were developed by the Center and can be found at www.stoprelationshipabuse.org.
    - Evaluations
      - Mentors in Violence Evaluations (Box 21)
      - Blank Evaluations (Box 21)
    - Handouts
      - Organizing College Campuses against Dating Abuse (Box 21)
      - CA Penal Code Charges (Box 21)
      - 12 Excuses of Perpetrators (Box 21)
      - Abuser Accountability (Box 21)